Guide to the Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. Papers 1808-1976 MS 438
New-York Historical Society
Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. papers
1808-1976
New-York Historical Society
Nathan, Edgar J., Jr., 1891-1965
MS 438
22.1 Linear feet in 18 record cartons, one flat box, and three oversize folders
The Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. papers include documents related to Nathan's civic service as a politician and communitarian, particularly within Jewish organizations. The collection includes speeches, correspondence, reports, and memorabilia from his time as a delegate to the 1938 New York Constitutional Convention, as Manhattan Borough President (1941-1945), and as a Justice to the New York Supreme Court (1946-1965), in addition to containing papers on his lifelong work in the Jewish community, particularly with Congregation Shearith Israel and the Jewish Theological Seminary. Print matter (much of it related to Judaism), photographs, general personal correspondence, and materials related to his time in the practice of law or in the service of the War Trade Board during World War I can also be found in the collection, along with limited materials related to Nathan's ancestry and early Jewish immigration to America.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in the following series:
Series I. Constitutional Convention, 1937-1941
Series II. Manhattan Borough Presidency, 1923-1945 (bulk, 1941-1945)
Series III. New York Supreme Court, 1938-1965
Series IV. Jewish Leadership, 1896-1967 (bulk, 1937-1965)
Series V. General Correspondence, 1900-1976
Series VI. Print Matter, 1881-1959 (bulk, 1890-1925)
Series VII. Memorabilia, 1808-1966
Biographical / Historical
Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. was born in New York City to parents Edgar J. Nathan, Sr. and Sara N. Solis on 28 August 1891. As a young man, Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. attended the Collegiate School, graduating in 1909 and receiving his A.B. degree from Williams College in 1913. Following in his father's footsteps, Nathan then studied law at Columbia University, where he received his L.L.B. After graduating from Columbia in 1916, Nathan briefly practiced law in his father's firm, Cardozo & Nathan (though relatives of Benjamin N. Cardozo worked for this firm, there are no records in this collection of Benjamin N. Cardozo in conjunction with Cardozo & Nathan), before marrying his lifelong wife, Mabel Unterberg, in 1917, with whom he would have two sons: Edgar J. Nathan, III and Frederick S. Nathan. When World War I began, he got a job at the War Trade Board, where he remained for two years. He climbed the ranks of his department, becoming the Chief of the Division of Restricted Imports before he resigned to return to the practice of law at Cardozo & Nathan.
Nathan, a direct descendant of Abraham de Lucena, one of the 13 original Jewish settlers in America, came from a very prestigious bloodline with deep ties to the United States, New York City, Judaism, and Shearith Israel—the earliest Jewish congregation in America, which was founded by Nathan's ancestors upon their arrival in New Amsterdam in 1654. As a result, Nathan dedicated large portions of his life to Jewish service and held positions of power in various Jewish organizations, including such titles as Vice-President, and later President, of Shearith Israel (for much of his life), Director of the Jewish Theological Seminary, Director and Vice-President of the American Jewish Historical Society, Secretary of the Jewish Family Service, President of the League of Fraternal and Benevolent Organizations of the Jewish Education Committee, and Director and President of The Judeans, among others. Nathan also did philanthropic work outside of the Jewish community, working as Director of the Goodwill Industries of New York and Honorary Director of the Knickerbocker Hospital in addition to donating large sums of money to various organizations, including his alma maters, all three of which (in addition to the Jewish Theological Seminary) eventually granted him awards or honorary degrees.
Though Nathan attempted to secure a position as Assistant Attorney General in 1920, it was not until 1937 that he was elected to his first political office, as a Republican delegate to the New York Constitutional Convention. There, he was on the Committees on the Judiciary, Bill of Rights, and Cities, where he worked with such notable politicians as Al Smith and Robert Wagner. One year later, in 1939, he ran for a vacant position on the New York Supreme Court, but failed to obtain the office, and so returned to the practice of law.
In 1941, Nathan successfully ran for Manhattan Borough President on the Republican and Fusion Party tickets. While in office, from 1941-1945, he worked alongside Mayor Fiorello La Guardia and Robert Moses on post-war construction works, including the East River (FDR) Drive and plans for the proposed Lower Manhattan Expressway (LOMEX), though it was never built. When he ran for reelection in 1946 and was ousted, he briefly joined the law firm of Gale, Bernays, Falk, Eisner, & Nathan, before Governor Thomas Dewey appointed him to a vacant seat on the New York Supreme Court, in the First Judicial District, in March 1946. That November, Nathan was officially elected to fill the vacancy for a fourteen-year term, and eventually, in 1960, he ran successfully for reelection. He served on the court past the retirement age, remaining on the bench until his death on 30 April 1965.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated by Frederic S. Nathan and Edgar J. Nathan, III in September 1980.
Scope and Contents
The Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. papers are comprised primarily of documents related to Edgar J. Nathan's work in civic service, both in terms of his involvement in New York politics and his active Jewish life. The collection includes papers—including correspondence, speeches, campaign materials, and reports on his accomplishments in office—for the three main stages of Nathan's political life, beginning with his time as a delegate to the 1938 New York Constitutional Convention and proceeding to his tenure as Manhattan Borough President in the early 1940s and New York Supreme Court Justice from 1946 until his death in 1965. During the years of Nathan's political service, he came into contact and formed relationships with a variety of influential political figures, including Dwight D. Eisenhower, Fiorello La Guardia, Robert Moses, Al Smith, Robert Wagner, Nelson Rockefeller, and Thomas Dewey. Thus, the collection includes correspondence with some of these men, though in other cases Nathan possessed only their signatures or impersonal notes from their offices. The collection also includes a significant amount of correspondence with Nathan's cousin, Supreme Court Justice Benjamin N. Cardozo.
In regards to Nathan's Jewish life, the collection contains documents—mainly souvenir programs, correspondence, speeches, and print matter—from a variety of organizations with which he was intimately involved, most prominently Shearith Israel (also known as the Spanish and Portuguese Congregation) and the Jewish Theological Seminary (JTS). The papers include extensive correspondence and memorabilia from major events in each organization's history, including Shearith Israel's (and worldwide) tercentenary celebrations commemorating the 300th anniversary of the arrival of Jews in America, the Jewish Theological Seminary's semi-centennial anniversary, and, in the case of Shearith Israel, stretching as far back as the consecration of their current house of worship in 1896.
The collection is also home to a sizable quantity of Nathan's personal correspondence and bills, most of which originate from the mid-20th century, as well as photographs, accumulated books (mostly on Jewish topics), and personal memorabilia, some of which pertains to preceding generations of the Nathan family—including, but not limited to, information on early Jewish immigration to the United States that traces the genealogies of the Nathan, Gomez, Seixas and Solis families.
For more information on early Jewish families that were related to the Nathans, see the New-York Historical Society's collection of the Hendricks Family papers.
Related Materials
Other materials related to the Nathan family can be found in the Hendricks Family papers, particularly in Subseries IX.F and IX.G.
Jews -- New York (State) -- New York.; Judaism; Local elections -- New York (State) -- New York.; Public works -- New York (State) -- New York.; Sephardim; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government.; New York (State) -- Politics and government.; Black-and-white photographs.; Books; Certificates.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diplomas; Ephemera.; Genealogies (histories); Pamphlets.; Receipts (financial records).; Speeches (documents).; Scrapbooks.; Burlingham, Charles C. (Charles Culp), 1858-1959; Cardozo, Benjamin N. (Benjamin Nathan), 1870-1938; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947; Moses, Robert, 1888-1981; Nathan, Edgar J., Jr., 1891-1965; Nathan (Family: New York, N.Y.); Congregation Shearith Israel (New York, N.Y.); Jewish Theological Seminary of America; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.). Office of the President; New York (State). Constitutional Convention (1938); New York (State). Supreme Court (1st Judicial District); United States. War Trade Board
- Series I. Constitutional Convention, 1937-1941; 1.6 Linear feet in two record cartons and an oversize folder
  Arrangement
  The series is organized in rough chronological order, beginning with campaign materials and election congratulations, followed by general correspondence, proposed amendments, and clippings on the convention, and ending with post-convention correspondence. Print matter and oversize materials complete the series.
  Scope and Contents
  The series is comprised of materials related to Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s position as delegate to the New York State Constitutional Convention in 1938. Much of the series constitutes documents regarding the 1937 election, including voting schedules and results, colorful district maps, candidate promotional materials and other ephemera, and correspondence in light of Nathan's victory. However, the series also includes correspondence about the convention itself, such as a letter from Nathan to his wife, Mabel, on the daily routine at the convention, fairly extensive records on amendments proposed in Albany, and a souvenir poster signed by the members of the Committee on the Judiciary (especially significant are the signatures of Al Smith and Robert Wagner). Post-convention correspondence, which is also included in the series, is primarily in regards to dinner reunion plans and two funerals for former delegates to the convention. Additionally, the series contains 11 of the original 12 volumes of reading material sent out to the delegates in preparation for their duties, which mainly concern foundational information on U.S. government and constitutional history.
  - Campaign Materials (2 folders of 3), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Campaign Materials (Folder 3 of 3), 1937 (Box Oversize Small, Folder 2)
    Oversize 1937 Borough of Manhattan election schedule, Republican ballot instructional manual and oversize maps of 7th and 11th Manhattan Assembly Districts.
  - Congratulations on Election, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Misc. Constitutional Convention Correspondence, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes 1938 letter from Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. to wife on daily routine during Constitutional Convention.
  - Proposed Amendments (Folder 1 of 2), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Contains name-embossed book of proposed amendments at the convention with Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s annotations.
  - Proposed Amendments (Folder 2 of 2), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings (2 folders), 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    Folder 7 includes a clipping about World War I.
  - Post-Constitutional Convention Correspondence (2 folders), 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Constitutional Committee Reports, Vol. 1-10 and 12, 1938 (Box 17, Volume 1-11)
    Volumes include, New York State Constitution Annotated, Amendments Proposed to New York Constitution, Constitutions of the States and United States, State and Local Government in New York, New York City Government Functions and Problems, Problems Relating to Bill of Rights and General Welfare, Problems Relating to Legislative Organization and Powers, Problems Relating to Executive Administration and Powers, Problems Relating to Judicial Administration and Organization, Problems Relating to Taxation and Finance, and an index. All volumes inscribed with Edgar J. Nathan, III's name and address.
  - Constitutional Committee Note, 1938 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    Contains copies of note from Constitutional Committee Chairman Charles Poletti on the purpose of the committee reports. Originally enclosed in accompanying volumes.
  - Oversize Constitutional Convention Seating Map, 1938 (Box Oversize Small, Folder 2)
  - Oversize Committee on the Judiciary Poster, 1938 (Box Oversize Small, Folder 2)
    Features the signatures of all members of the committee, as well as other prominent New York politicians who were involved with the convention, including Al Smith and Robert Wagner.
- Series II. Manhattan Borough Presidency, 1923-1945; 4.8 Linear feet in five record cartons, one flat box, and in oversize folders
  The documents remain almost entirely in their original subject folders, though many of the folders were previously unlabeled and titles were primarily devised by the processing archivist, with the exception of the folders containing Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s speeches and his plans for the arterial highway bill, which retain original labels. Items of other formats, including print matter, newspaper clippings, photographs, and oversized posters, are listed at the end of the series.
  The series consists of documents related to Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s tenure as Manhattan Borough President, which lasted from 1941-1945. These include campaign materials, related correspondence (including communication with various influential politicians such as Mayor Fiorello La Guardia and Robert Moses), construction plans, speeches (many on Jewish topics or for Jewish audiences), financial reports, Board of Estimate meeting minutes, and memorabilia from New York City events, including a 1945 dinner honoring then-general Dwight D. Eisenhower. The series also contains photographs, clippings, and scrapbooks. Much of the material is about World War II and post-war construction works, including the construction of the East River Drive (FDR) and the proposed Lower Manhattan Expressway (LOMEX), which was never built.
  - Congratulations on Nomination, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Campaign Materials (Folder 1 of 2), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Election materials from 1941 campaign for Manhattan Borough Presidency, including biographies, press releases, and a Speaker's Handbook re: La Guardia Administration accomplishments, among other documents.
  - Campaign Materials (Folder 2 of 2), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Campaign materials from failed 1945 campaign for re-election to office of Manhattan Borough President, including campaign song, list of construction works, endorsements, and remarks.
  - Misc. Manhattan Borough Presidency Documents, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes information about East River Drive opening ceremonies, plans for other post-war construction works, Manhattan Borough President ID badge, memo of understanding with Terminal Market of New York related to improvements in the Washington Wholesale Market, and correspondence from Mayor La Guardia, as well as a clipping on Thomas Dewey's campaign for the U.S. Presidency.
  - Honorary Dinner Memorabilia (Folder 1 of 2), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Documents from 1945 dinner honoring General Dwight D. Eisenhower, including telegram from Marie La Guardia, Mayor La Guardia's wife, inviting Mabel Nathan, Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s wife, to a luncheon with the women of General Eisenhower's party, flowers from the table decoration, and a picture of General Eisenhower with Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. in the background. Also contains a letter from Charles C. Burlingham.
  - Honorary Dinner Memorabilia (Folder 2 of 2), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Programs and other mementos from 1945 dinners honoring General Jonathan M. Wainwright and Admiral Chester W. Nimitz, including a photograph of Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. on a dais with various important New York State politicians (such as Governor Thomas Dewey). Also includes a parking map from Navy Day.
  - Arterial Highway Bill, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Includes tense correspondence between Edgar J. Nathan, Jr., Mayor Fiorello La Guardia, Robert Moses, and other important New York City officials regarding a disagreement over control of post-war highway construction works.
  - Proposed Lower Manhattan Crosstown Express Highway (Folder 1 of 2), 1943 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Contains book of plans drafted by Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. for Lower Manhattan Crosstown Express Highway (LOMEX).
  - Proposed Lower Manhattan Crosstown Express Highway (Folder 2 of 2), 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Contains papers previously enclosed within Folder 18 book, including correspondence between Edgar Jr. Nathan and various important New York officials (Mayor LaGuardia, Governor Thomas Dewey, Robert Moses) as well as plans for crosstown expressway.
  - East River Drive Books, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Contains 1940 book on East River Drive plans and a 1942 booklet commemorating the Opening of East River Drive and Commercial Marginal Way.
  - Post-War Construction Print Matter, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Includes, among other documents, the proposed post-war works program published by the City Planning Commission; a booklet on the Parks Department's proposed reconstruction of Battery Park; the Parks Department's report on scheduling of postwar improvements; Nathan's white paper "Plan to Alleviate Traffic Congestion in Midtown Manhattan"; and the Manhattan Borough Works' illustrated description of the new municipal asphalt plant.
  - New York Advancing: Victory Edition, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Book on accomplishments of Mayor La Guardia's tenure, signed by Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. and contains much information about post-war construction in New York City.
  - Board of Estimate Minutes and Other Documents (Folder 1 of 2), 1943 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Contains binder labeled "The Committee on Grievances: Bar Association," but documents inside are entirely related to 1943 Board of Estimate meetings.
  - Board of Estimate Minutes and Other Documents (Folder 2 of 2), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Borough of Manhattan Fiscal Reports (Folder 1 of 5), 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Borough of Manhattan Fiscal Reports (4 folders of 5), 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
    The fifth folder holds the Borough President's financial report for 1944-45.
  - Speeches—Home (3 folders of 5), 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
    Many speeches written for Manhattan Borough Presidency events, but also many written for Jewish audiences or with Jewish themes.
  - Speeches—Home (Folder 4 of 5), 1925-1944 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Contains speech materials, including drafts of jokes and Jewish articles. Also contains copies of articles written by Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. on post-war construction.
  - Speeches—Home (Folder 5 of 5), 1923-1945 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    Clippings, mostly featuring Judaism.
  - Speeches (4 folders), 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 9-12)
    Folder 12 contains speeches and articles written in support of Governor Thomas E. Dewey's presidential campaign against Franklin D. Roosevelt.
  - Reference Letters (2 folders), 1940-1945 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - Photographs, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Includes photos of Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. with various other men, including New York Secretary of State Thomas J. Curran. Also includes photos of Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. giving gifts to Jewish orphans and changing a Broadway street sign to say "Bondway" in honor of the third war loan drive.
  - Clippings (5 folders), 1941-1945 (Box 19, Folder 10-14)
  - Oversize Washington Eagle Clipping on Endorsements, 1941 (Box Oversize Small, Folder 2)
  - 2 Oversize Campaign Posters, c. 1941-1946 (Box Oversize Small, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbooks (2 volumes of 5), 1941-1943 (Box 9, Volume 4-5)
    Contain clippings, dinner programs, photos, and other assorted documents from Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s tenure as Manhattan Borough President.
  - Scrapbooks (3 volumes of 5), 1944-1945 (Box 14, Volume 3-5)
  - Meeting Attendance and Voting Records (Flat Box), 1941-1945 (Box 18, Volume 1)
    Contains log of attendence and voting records for all borough presidents at joint meetings during Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s tenure.
- Series III. New York Supreme Court, 1938-1965; 3.8 Linear feet in five record cartons and in oversize folders
  The documents remain in their original subject folders, except for those that were relocated by the processing archivist from miscellaneous folders. However, the folders were originally unlabeled and titles were devised by the archivist. The subject files begin with campaign materials and correspondence from Edgar J. Nathan's appointment, election, and re-election to the New York Supreme Court, then advance to correspondence regarding cases that Nathan presided over, followed by reference letters that he wrote during his tenure. The series ends with clippings and seven scrapbooks, which are filled with clippings from law journals on Nathan's cases.
  The series is made up of documents that relate to Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s tenure as a New York Supreme Court Justice, which lasted from 1946 until his death in 1965, as well as his failed campaign for the New York Supreme Court in 1939. These include promotional materials, sympathy and congratulatory letters (in response to Nathan's failure in 1939, appointment by Thomas Dewey to fill a vacancy in 1946, official election to the court that November, and his re-election in 1960), information on his cases in the form of clippings, scrapbooks, and correspondence, and general correspondence, including the vast quantity of reference letters that Nathan wrote while in office. The series also contains photographs and other miscellaneous documents, including an interview transcript in which Nathan speaks at length about his genealogy as a descendant of Abraham de Lucena.
  - Election Materials (3 folders), 1939-1960 (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
  - Congratulations on Nomination to NY Supreme Court (2 folders), 1939 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
    Includes endorsement from The New York Post, notes from family (including sons at college, Emily and Solomon Solis Cohen), congratulatory note from Charles C. Burlingham, and some enclosed four-leaf clovers. Includes letters from some New York politcians, including Edward Corsi and contemporary Manhattan Borough President Stanley M. Issacs. Some notes are addressed to Nathan's wife, Mabel.
  - Sympathy Letters on Election Defeat, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Like Folders 19-20, contains letters from New York politicians, including Stanley M. Isaacs. Contains many references to the political machine of Tammany Hall and political polarization.
  - Congratulations on Appointment to NY Supreme Court (6 folders), 1946 (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
  - Congratulations on Election to NY Supreme Court (6 folders), 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 7-12)
  - Supreme Court Cases and Correspondence (4 folders), 1946-1964 (Box 3, Folder 13-16)
    Folder 15 contains a letter from Governor Thomas E. Dewey and correspondence related to injuries Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. sustained in an automobile accident. Also contains rosters of certified psychologists and members of the National Republican Club. Folder 16 contains a clothing catalogue for robes.